<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mis-led King, and a memorable Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E90_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16635</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860068</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112175</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89176)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112175)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E90[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mis-led King, and a memorable Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb. 18 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Richard --  II, --  King of England, 1367-1400.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Richard II, 1377-1399 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112175:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112175:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A mis-le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King, and a memorable <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis preſent occaſion ſo opportunely befitting me, I am reſolved to treat of that which hath been omitted, and ſlipped out of memory long ſince, concerning divers and ſundry changes and alterations in <hi>England</hi> in former times: Nor will it be any wayes burthenſome to write of that, whereby every good and carefull Reader may learne to avoid diverſities of miſeries, and the danger and feare of cruell death. I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpeake of that which hath laine hid in the darkſome ſhade of forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, concerning men who have been led away by the deceitfull path o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Covetouſneſſe, and have come to a moſt ſhamefull and ignominious death: a famous example to deterre all men from practiſing thoſe or the like courſes.</p>
            <p>ABout the yeare of Chriſt 1386. at ſuch time as <hi>Richard,</hi> the ſecond of that name, then in prime of his youth, ſwayed the Imperiall S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>er of our Realme, there flouriſhed famous in his Court certaine Peeres, though ſome of them not of any honourable deſcent, yet favoured by fortunes; by name, <hi>Alexander Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il;</hi> Archbiſhop of Yorke; <hi>Robert Vee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> D. of Ireland; <hi>Michael de la Poole,</hi> Earle of Suffolke, then Lord Chancellour; <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Treſſilian,</hi> Lord chiefe Juſtice of England; and <hi>Nicholas Brambre,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Major of London.</p>
            <p>Theſe men being raiſed from mean eſtates, by the ſpeciall favour of the King, and advanced to the degree of privie Counſellours, were the men who had the only rule of the Common-wealth; which they, under the King, governed for ſome ſmall ſpace, with carefull diligence, meriting thereby deſerved commendations. But not long did they thus ſteere the Ship of the Kingdome: for many of them being of inferiour ranke by birth, not having their veines dignified with the ſtreames of noble blood; they were the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner enticed with the fibidinous baits of voluptuouſneſſe, and infected with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable itch of avarice: inſomuch, that deſpiſing the authority of the King, and neglecting the commodity of the Realme, but onely deſiring to keep up the Revenues of the Kingdome, ſo wrought, that by their policie, the King is impoveriſhed, the Treaſury exhauſted; the Commons murmure at the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of Tenths; Levies, and Subſidies; the Peeres repine to ſee themſelves
<pb facs="tcp:112175:2"/>
diſgraced, and their inferiours honored; and in a word, the whole Kingdome endures an univerſall miſery.</p>
            <p>The Nobility ſeeing the miſerable eſtate wherein the Kingdome lay, blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing as it were to death, urged their King to ſummon a Parliament; which was done ſhortly after. In which amongſt many other Acts, the afore-named <hi>Michael de la Poole</hi> is diſmiſt of his Chancellorſhip; and being accuſed of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and many points of injuſtice, as Bribery, Extortion, and the like, he was ſoon caſt into the Caſtle of Windſor, and all his lands, which were of no ſmall Revenue, were conſiſeated to the King. Neither did the Parliament here give over, but provided further for the whole State; by the mutuall conſent of the King and Prelates, Barons and Commons, with an unanimous conjunction, they conſtitute and give plenary and abſolute power to certaine Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as well of the Spiritualty as Temporalty, for the ordering and diſpoſing of the publique affaires, according, as ſhall ſeem beſt and moſt neceſſary for the deſperate eſtate of the Common-wealth, to depreſſe civill diſſentions, and to paciſie and appeaſe the grudgings of the people.</p>
            <p>Of the Spiritualty were choſen the Archbiſhop of Canterbury, the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Biſhop of York, the Biſhop of Ely, lately made Chancelor of England, the Biſhop of Wincheſter; Biſhop of Hereford, Lord Treaſurer; Biſhop of Exeter, Abbot of Waltham, and the Lord <hi>Iohn</hi> of Waltham.</p>
            <p>Of the Laity were elected the Duke of York, the Earle of Arundel, the Lord <hi>Goltham,</hi> the Lord <hi>Scroop,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Devoureux</hi> Knight: theſe as men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent in vertue, were choſen by the generall Suffrage, and ſworn to carry themſelves as dutifull and obedient ſubjects in all their actions. And it was further enacted, That if any ſhould refuſe or diſobey the Ordinances ſo made for publick good, the puniſhment of his firſt offence, ſhould be the coſiſcation of his goods; and for the ſecond, the loſſe of life. Thus diſpoſing of all things for the beſt, the Parliament being diſſolved, euery man returned to his owne houſe.</p>
            <p>Soon after, the afore-named Chancelor, with others of their conſederates, being moved with implacable fury againſt the Statute of the late Parliament, they buzzed into the Kings eares, that the Statutes lately enacted, were very prejudiciall to the honour of his Crowne, and much derogatory to his Princely Prerogative: inſomuch that he ſhould not have power, without the conſent of the new-appointed Commiſſioners, to doe any thing befitting a King; no, not ſo much as to beſtow a largeſſe, a principall meanes to gain the peoples love, upon any, though never ſo well deſerving.</p>
            <p>By theſe and other the like impious inſtigations, with which the Divel (as never unmindful of the end of thoſe, who by their lives do prove themſelves) did continually ſupply them, they practiſed to annihilate and diſanull theſe
<pb facs="tcp:112175:2"/>
Acts of the Parliament, which ſeemed any wayes to abbreviate or curb their uſurped authority.</p>
            <p>And firſt, by their ſerpentine tongues, ambitious projects, flattery painted out with gloſing diſcourſes, and covered over with the ſhadow of vigilan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> for the good of the Kingdome, they ſo be witched the noble inclination of the youthfull King, whom they induced to beleeve, that all the ill they did, was a generall good, that he began to diſtalte, and at laſt to abhorte the laſt paſſed Acts, as treacherous plots, and moſt wicked devices.</p>
            <p>Next, they ſtudied how to ingroſſe all, or the moſt part of the wealth and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Kingdome into their own coffers; and to the ſame end, dealt ſo cunningly, yet pleaſingly with the King, that hee gave to the D. of Ireland, <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Bloys,</hi> the heir of the Dutchy of Britaine, and his ranſome; to others, Townes; to others, Cities; to others, Lands; to others, Money, amounting to the ſumme of 100000 Markes, to the great impoveriſhment both of King and Kingdome: neither did theſe King-eaters and Realm-devourers any thing regard it, but ſetting unskilfull and inſufficient Captaines and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours over Townes and Forts ſo obtained, gave occaſion to the enemies of the Crowne to ſurpriſe them, and diſpoſſeſſe the King of them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, vilifying the dignity of the King, contrary to their allegeance, they drew the King to ſweare, that with all his power, during his life, hee ſhould maintain and deſend them from all their enemies, whether forraigne or domeſtick.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, whereas it was enacted by the laſt Parliament, that the King at certain ſeaſonable times, and when his leaſure would permit him, ſhould ſit at Weſtminſter with his Councell there, to conſult of the publique affaires; through the perſwaſions of the aforeſaid Conſpirators, hee was drawne into the moſt remoteſt parts of the Realme, to the great diſparagement of the fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of thoſe honorable, grave, and faithfull Peeres, late made joynt Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, in whoſe hands the whole ſafety and proſperity of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth did recide.</p>
            <p>And when as the Lord Chancelour, the Lord Treaſurer, Keeper of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Seale, or any other of the Privie Councell, came to relate any of their owne actions, or the ſtate of the Realme, they could not bee granted free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, unleſſe they related the buſineſſe in the preſence and hearing of the conſpirators, who were alwayes ready to upbraid them if they uttered any thing that diſpleaſed them, and to command them for any thing (though moſt nefarious) that did content them: for thus could they the ſooner learne and dive into the acts of the Commiſſioners, and the better find evaſions for their accuſations: Furthermore, when as the King in company of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators went in progreſſe towards the parts of Cheſhire, Wales, and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire, they made proclamation in the Kings name, throughout the Shires as
<pb facs="tcp:112175:3"/>
they journied, That all Barous, Knights, Eſquires, with the greateſt part of the Communalty able to beare armes, ſhould ſpeedily repaire to the King for his defence againſt the power of the Comiſſioners, chiefly of the Duke of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter and the Earle of Arundel; becauſe they above the reſt, did with their chiefeſt endevours, ſtudy to ſuppreſſe &amp; quell the devices of the conſpirators.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, contrary to the aforeſaid Acts, they cauſed the D. of Ireland to bee treated chiefe Juſtice of Cheſter, thereby ſelling juſtice as they liſted, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the guiltleſſe, and remitting the guilty, never reſpecting or looking unto the equall ballance of juſtice, but poizing downe the ſcales with heaps of Bribery.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, by the procurement of the confederates, they cauſed certain honeſt perſons, who would not conſent to their extortions, to be called and ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their Court, and thereto anſwer to certaine falſe accuſations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were unjuſtly charged by perjuring hirelings; of which men ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, ſome were put to death, ſome caſt into priſon, all were vexed and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with delayes, length of their journey to and fro, and exceſſive charges; neither were they eaſed of any theſe burthens, unleſſe they would part with round ſummes of money to the D. and his Complices.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, they gave pardons under the Brod Seal, to Felons, Murderers, and ſuch like, only with this condition, that they ſhould murther any whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they thought did miſlike their exaction.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, they taught the countrey of Ireland to look to its priſtine eſtate, I mean, of having a King; for they plotted how to have the Duke created King of Ireland: And for the confirmation of which their deſigne, they allured the King to ſend his letters to the Pope.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, the aforeſaid <hi>Nicholas Brambre,</hi> in the time of his Majoralty, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two and twenty to be falſly accuſed of Felonies, and laid into Newgate, under pretext and colour of divers crimes, and in the ſilent and dead time of the night to be faſt bound, and by a ſtrong hand to be carried into Kent, to a place commonly called <hi>Fawlocks,</hi> and then to have their heads ſtruck off, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one who being favoured by the murtherers, ſafely eſcaped; the blood of the teſt died the ſtreames of a ſmall Rivelet adjoyning.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, ſoon after, to adde one miſchief to another, they ſent letters under the Kings Sigret, to the Major of London, by <hi>Iohn Rippon</hi> Clerke, with a certain libell, or ſchedule incloſed in the ſaid letters, the tenor of which is as followeth.</p>
            <p>That the afore-named three Commiſſioners, <hi>viz.</hi> the Duke of Gloceſter, the Earles of Arundel and Warwick, and other of the Councell, were to bee arreſted, indicted, condemned, and put to a lamentable death as being ſuch as had conſpired againſt the King, againſt his prevogative &amp; againſt his Crown and Imperiall dignity; and to this they did in a manner conſtrain the King to
<pb facs="tcp:112175:3"/>
aſſent unto. Upon receit of theſe letters, the Major and Aldermen of the Citie of London, called a Common Councell, wherein they conſulted what courſe were beſt to be taken in this matter; and after long debate, <hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> it was on all ſides agreed, to deny and not to ſuffer that cruell and unheard of Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Complot to be executed.</p>
            <p>It ever happeneth, one wicked act drawes on a ſecond, and that ſecond a third, and ſo forwards, till the weight crackes the ſupporter.</p>
            <p>Therefore the ſail Conſpirators being blinded with raſhneſſe, principally ſent letters by <hi>Iohn Godfrey</hi> Knight, to the King of France, the Kings adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, to conclude a five yeares truce, ſhould come over to Callis, and from thence ſhould ſend for the Duke of Gloceſter, the Earles of Arundell and Warwick, and for ſome other of the Commiſſioners, as though the King were unwilling to determine of any thing without their advice; and being thus circumvented, ſhould be condemned as traytors, and ſo put to an ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and cruell death.</p>
            <p>And for doing and performing of theſe things, the King of France was to recover all the Caſtles, Townes, and Lands lying in theſe countries, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the King of England. To prove theſe things to be true, there were certaine writings produced by the Commiſſioners, wherein were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained letters from the King of France to the King of England, and from the conſpirators in the King of Englands name, to the King of France.</p>
            <p>Moreover, there were other letters intercepted, directed to the ſaid King of France, the ſubſtance whereof was, to incite the King of France to leavre a puiſſant power into England, againſt the Duke of Gloceſter, the Earles of Arundel and Warwicke, and the reſt of the Commiſſioners, and all thoſe that did either countenance or favour the ſaid ſtatute and Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>Now here concluding their diveliſh conſpiracie, the five aforeſaid conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators departed from Weſtminſter to the Caſtle of Nottingham, and ſent a Writ for <hi>Robert Beale,</hi> Lord chiefe Juſtice of the Common-Pleas, <hi>Iohn Holt, Reger Fulthorp &amp; Will. Burleigh,</hi> Judges of the ſaid Court, and for <hi>John Locton,</hi> the Kings Serjeant at Law: who being come into the Councell-chamber, not knowing what they were ſent for, the aforeſaid conſpirators cauſed the gates and doores of the Caſtle to be ſhut, and then propounded theſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions following unto them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether thoſe Statutes, Ordinances, and Commiſſion, made in the late Parliament at Weſtminſter, were derogatory to the Kings dignity and Kingly Prerogative; and, becauſe they were to be puniſhed who did procure thoſe Conſtitutions, and did incite and move the King to conſent unto them, and did as much as in them lay to hinder the King from exerciſing his Royall Prerogative.</p>
            <p>To theſe and other the like queſtions, with a joynt conſent they anſwered,
<pb facs="tcp:112175:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> death as traytors, or elſe to endure ſome capitall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> witneſſe of which aſſertion, being terrified with the feare of preſent death, the aforeſaid Judges, together with <hi>Iohn Carey,</hi> Lord chiefe Baron of the Exchequer, they ſigned and ſealed a certaine writing in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a Proteſtation, in preſence of theſe witneſſes, <hi>Alex. Nevil,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>Bangor, Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Ireland, Michael</hi> Earle of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke, Iohn Rippon</hi> Clerke, and <hi>Iohn Blake</hi> Fruiterer, dated the 19 of <hi>September, Anno Dom.</hi> 1387. in the 11. yeare of the reigne of K. <hi>Richard</hi> 2. Then were they compelled to ſweare, that they ſhould keep the paſſages undiſcovered, upon pain of death; and ſo they had licence to depart.</p>
            <p>And that which is worſe, they cauſed the King to ſweare, That in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per perſon, with his whole power, he ſhould take revenge of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> of the two Earles and their adherents, by cauſing them to bee put to death.</p>
            <p>But, God inſpired into the hearts of the aforeſaid Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> the Earles of <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>Warwicke,</hi> the ſpirit of valour and magnanimity, who ſeeing the heap of ills that daily did ariſe by the practices of thoſe coſpirators, they ſet almoſt in every part of the Kingdome, intelligencers, who ſhould apprehend all Meſſengers, and intercept all letters of the Kings, or that went under the Kings name, and ſhould ſend them to the Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>And thus did they come to have intelligence of the whole plot of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators; all their Letters being indorced, with <hi>Glory bee to God on high, on earth peace, and good will towards men:</hi> and by comming to the knowledge of each circumſtance, they found, that the Kingdome was at the point of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; according to that Evangelicall ſaying, <hi>Every Kingdome divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelfe, ſhall be diſſolved:</hi> Wherefore they ſought for a remedy; every man according to his ability, levied a power for the preſervation of the King and Kingdome: all which forces being united, amounting to the number of 20000. fighting men, and couragiouſly reſolving to fruſtrate all the intended deſignes of the conſpirators, and to open the nut by cracking the ſhell, they divided their Army, committing part of it to the Earle of <hi>Arundel:</hi> who by night marched away with his Forces, and pitched his tents neer to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> there fortifying himſelf in the Forreſt adjoyning, till ſuch time as he had gained more convenient time, and greater force, by the comming of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts. On the other ſide, the conſpirators intending to prevent their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by power of a certaine Spirituall Commiſſion, and by vertue of certaine Letters Patents in the hands of the Conſpirators, though nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; yet to blind the people, they cauſed to be proclaimed throughout the whole Citie of <hi>London,</hi> that none upon paine of the forfeiture of all their goods, ſhould neither ſell, give, or communicate privatly or publickly, victual, armour, or any other neceſſaries to the Army of the Earle of <hi>Arundel,</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:112175:4"/>
ſhould barre them of ſuſtentation, comfort, or help, as Rebels to the King and countrey. But on the other ſide, they began to feare, when they were denied their hoped-for aid by the Major and Communalty of the Citie of <hi>London.</hi> And againe, they were troubled at the riſing of the Commoners, to invade them. Wherefore they counſelled the King to abſent himſent from the Parliament, (which was to begin at <hi>Candlemas</hi> next, according as the King and Commiſſioners had appointed it) and not conſult of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Kingdome, nor of his owne Eſtate, commodity or diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, unleſſe the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> the two Earles of <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> with the reſt of the Commiſſioners, would ſweare, That neither they, nor any in their name, ſhould accuſe them, or urge any accuſation againſt them.</p>
            <p>Not long after it happened, that the King, with the aforeſaid five Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, came from his Mannor at <hi>Sheeve,</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to Saint <hi>Edmonds</hi> Tombe, for the ſolemnizing of a Pilgrimage. The Major and Aldermen of the Citie of <hi>London</hi> met him on horſeback ſumptuouſly attired, honoring him very much.</p>
            <p>And when they came to the <hi>Mewes,</hi> they deſcended from their horſes, and went bare-foot to the Tombe of S. <hi>Edmond;</hi> where as the Chaplaine of the Commiſſioners, with the Abbot and Covent, met them with a ſtately Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the three Noble-men, <hi>viz.</hi> the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and the Earles of <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>Warwicke</hi> having muſtered their Troopes on the fourteenth of <hi>November,</hi> in the ſame yeare, at <hi>Waltham Croſſe,</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> and from thence ſent for the Commiſſioners that were there at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in Parliament with the King, ſending an accuſation in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the King, againſt the aforeſaid Conſpirators, <hi>viz.</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Duke of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Earle of <hi>Suffolke, Robert Triſilian,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Brambre;</hi> wherein they accuſed them of high treaſon: which their appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation they did offer to maintain, and that they were willing to proſecute the ſame; and to prove it to be true, they cauſed alſo the reſt of the Commiſſioners to ſubſcribe, as parties to their appellation.</p>
            <p>When theſe things came to the eares of the King, he ſent unto them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring to know what their requeſt was, and what they wiſhed to have been done: They returned anſwer thus: That they did deſire, that the Traytors which were alwayes about him, filling his eares with falſe reports, and did daily commit inſufferable crimes and injuries, might be rewarded with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment. And likewiſe craved, that they might have ſafe liberty of going and comming to his grace.</p>
            <p>When the King heard their requeſt, he gave them is Royall conſent, and commanded them to appeare at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and the King ſitting on his
<pb facs="tcp:112175:5"/>
Throne in the great Hall, the three aforeſaid Peeres Appellants with a great troop of Gentlemen, entred, &amp; making three lowly obeyſances, on their ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded knees, they reverenced the King: and drawing neere (the cauſe of their comming being alledged) they there againe appealed the Archbiſhop, Duke of Ireland, Earle Treaſurer, and <hi>Brambre</hi> of hightreaſon, according as they had done before at Waltham Croſſe; but they betaking themſelves to the private corners of the Palace, even as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> from the preſence of God, not having the heart to appeare, to juſtifie themſelves.</p>
            <p>The King called forth the Appellants, to prove and proſecute the Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, preſcribing them a day and place for the triall, which was to be on the day after <hi>Candlemas</hi> day; and in the mean time, the King commanded them upon their Honours, not any party to moleſt the other untill the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Ireland,</hi> under the guide of his grand Captaine the Divell, marching into Cheſhire, Lancaſhire, and Wales, raiſed a new power, amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the number of 6000 fighting men; from thence marched towards London with his Army, with a furious intent and reſolution to performe his bloody deſigne. And whilſt theſe plots were laid, the Appellants being ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly advertiſed thereof, raiſed a great power, and joyning with them the Earle of Derby, and the Earle of Nottingham, and other Commiſſioners, marched with long and wearied marches into a field neere a village called <hi>Whitney,</hi> at a place called <hi>Lockeford Bridge:</hi> In which field the Duke of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was with his Army, having a river on the one ſide of them, whereas they ſtood ready prepared to give an overthrow to the Appellants, and diſplaying the Kings Standard, contrary to the Lawes of the land. When they ſaw the Army of the Appellants march down from the mountaines, like a Hive of Bees, and with ſuch a violent fury, fear benummed them, and they were ſo amazed, that when they ſhould give the aſſault (God not ſuffering the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of blood) they ſtood like a Hive of Bees, or a flocke of Cattell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a head, without any ſtroke given, they flung down their Armes, and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelves to the mercy of the Appellants; and a few being ſlaine, and ſome drowned in the river, gave an eaſie victory to the Conquerours.</p>
            <p>When the newes of the victory was blowne to the eares of the reſt of the conſpirators, who were then ſtricken with feare, and carefull for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, under covert of the night, they fled by water to the Tower, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King along with them.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide <hi>Nicholas Brambre</hi> with a bold and reſolute courage, in the Kings name, cauſed all the gates of the Citie to be ſhut againſt the Apel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, and to be guarded with an able and ſufficient Watch: But theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and dauntleſſe members of the Common-wealth, marched towards <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to confer with the King; but when they heard that the ſaid <hi>Nicholas
<pb facs="tcp:112175:5"/>
Brambre</hi> had cauſed the gates of the Citie to be ſhut againſt them, and to be ſtrongly guarded, and that the whole Citie did purpoſe to keep them out, they ſtayed their reſolution.</p>
            <p>On the 27 day of <hi>September,</hi> they encamped themſelves in <hi>Clarkenwell,</hi> within the liberties of the Citie of <hi>London.</hi> And when as the Major, with the Citizens, came unto them with pleaſing words, promiſing unto them all that the Citie could affoord with reaſon and equity; the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> ſaid, Now I know, that liers ſpeak nothing but lies, neither can any man hinder them from the relating: whereupon by a joynt conſent in the evening, they removed their tents, and pitched them before divers gates of the Citie.</p>
            <p>On the morrow there happened an enterview between the King and the Appellants, ſo far, that they opened their mindes one to the other: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the King loathed to ſpeak with them, with ſuch a rabble of men, and in regard of an intolerable boldnes, &amp; ſome quarrell which was like to ariſe; and on the other ſide, refuſing to go out of the <hi>Tower</hi> to ſpeak with them, and the Appellants fearing ſome violence or wrong to be offered to them, would not ſpeak with the king without a ſtrong guard of valiant warriors. Therefore the moſt wiſe of the Appellants, after divers diſputations had, reſolved to go and confer with the King: but firſt they ſent a ſtrong Troop well armed, to ſearch al the Corners &amp; Caves of the <hi>Tower;</hi> and relation being made of the ſafety of the place, with a ſelected band of valiant Cavaliers, they entred the <hi>Tower;</hi> and ſeizing the gates, &amp; placing a guard, appeared before the King; and there the third time appealed the aforeſaid conſpirators in the ſame ſort and forme as before: which appellation being ended, the King ſwore, That he would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to their counſell as a good King, and a juſt Judge, ſo farre as the rule of Law, Reaſon, and Equity did require.</p>
            <p>Then it was publiſhed and made knowne in the preſence of the King, and throughout the Dominions, that on the morrow after <hi>Candlemas</hi> day, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid conſpirators ſhould perſonally appeare, to anſwere to the appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereby they were charged of ſo many treaſons.</p>
            <p>They expulſed divers of the Officers of the Houſhold; <hi>viz.</hi> in the place of <hi>John Beauchamp,</hi> Steward of the Houſhold, they appointed <hi>John Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vex,</hi> Knight, one of the Commiſſioners; <hi>Peter Courtney,</hi> Knight, was made Chamberlaine in ſtead of <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Ireland.</hi> And the foreſaid <hi>John de Beauchamp, Simon de Burleigh,</hi> Vice Chamberlaine, <hi>Iohn Saliſbury, Thomas Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, Iames Barats William Ellingham,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Nagworth,</hi> Knights; and Officers of the Clergy, <hi>(viz.) Richard Mecford</hi> Secretary, <hi>Iohn Blake</hi> Deane of the Chappell, <hi>John Lincolne</hi> Chancellor of the Exchequer, and <hi>Iohn Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Clerke of the Chappell, were kept under arreſt too, and were as parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in the aforeſaid Treaſon; for that they knowing and having intelligence of the ſaid Conſpiracy, they did not diſcover them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:112175:6"/>
And thus this hideous brood of Monſters, ſo often ſhaken, was quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne.</p>
            <p>And on the Vigill of the Purification of Saint <hi>Mary,</hi> in the Privy Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at Weſtminſter, be joynt conſent of all the Commiſſioners, the aforeſaid <hi>Iohn <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Iohn Holt, Roger Fulthorp, William Burleigh, Iohn Locton,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Carey</hi> were diſplaced from their Offices, and without any further adoe arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of Treaſon, and by the command of the Chancelor were clapt into the Tower; and <hi>Roger Carleton</hi> in the place of <hi>Belknap, Walter Clapton</hi> in the place of <hi>Treſſilian,</hi> were conſtituted.</p>
            <p>The great Parliament began the ſecond of February following, in this manner: All the Peeres, as well of the Spiritualty as of the Temporalty, being aſſembled in the great Hall at Weſtminſter, the King ſoone after came and ſate downe in his Throne; and after him appeared the five Noblemen Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, (the fame of whoſe admired worth ecchoed through all the Land) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Houſe in their coſtly robes, leading one another hand in hand, with an innumerable company following them; and beholding where the King ſate, all at once, with ſubmiſſive geſtures they reverenced the King. <hi>Brambre</hi> was taken a little before, and caſt into the Gaole of Glouceſter.</p>
            <p>The Clergy then placing themſelves on the right hand, and the Nobility on the left hand of the King, according to the ancient cuſtome of the High Court of Parliament; the Lord Chancelor ſtanding with his back toward the King, by the Kings command declared the cauſe of their ſummons to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: which being ended, the five aforeſaid Appellants ariſing, declared their aforeſaid Appellation by the mouth of <hi>Robert Pleaſington</hi> their Speaker, who thus ſpake: Behold, the Duke of Glouceſter comes to purge himſelfe of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which are laid to his charge by the conſpirators. To whom the Lord Chancelor, by the command of the King anſwered: My Lord Duke, the King conceiveth ſo honourably of you, that he cannot be induced to beleeve, that you, who are of affinity to him in a collaterall line, ſhould attempt any treaſon againſt his ſacred Majeſty. The Duke with his foure Companions, upon their knees humbly gave thankes to the King for his gracious opinion of their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity.</p>
            <p>Then after ſilence proclaimed, they aroſe, and delivered in certain Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in writing, wherein were contained the particularity of the Treaſon.</p>
            <p>When the Articles were read, the Appellants requeſted the King, that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemnation might be given againſt the Conſpirators, and they to receive the guerdon of their deſerts; which the King promiſed to grant.</p>
            <p>And when the third day came of their proceedings againſt the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, the Lord Chancelor in the name of the Clergy, in open Parliament made an Oration, ſhewing that they could not by any meanes be preſent at the proceeding, whereas there is any cenſure of death to be paſſed. For
<pb facs="tcp:112175:6"/>
the confirmation whereof, they delivered in a Proteſtation, which being read, they ſpake, That neither in reſpect of any favour, nor for feare of any mans hate, nor in hope of any reward, they did deſire to abſent themſelves; but onely that they were bound by the Canon not to bee preſent at any mans arraignment or condemnation. They likewiſe ſent their Proteſtation to the Chappell of the Abbey, where the Commons ſate; which was allowed of. And then, when the Appellants called for juſtice againſt the Conſpirators, the Lords of the Spiritualty aroſe, and went into the Kings Chamber neere adjoyning.</p>
            <p>But the King being moved in conſcience, and in charity, perceiving that in every worke they are to remember the end; and being willing (contrary to the rigour of the Law) to favour rather theſe that were guilty, then the actors in that Treaſon, if they were able to alledge any thing in their defence cauſed the Proceſſe to ceaſe: but the Peeres (being earneſt) requeſted, That no buſineſſe paſt, preſent, or to come, might be debated, untill this Treaſon were adjudged; to which Petition the King graciouſly granted his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>On the 11. day of February, when nothing could be alledged, nor no wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe produced, in juſtification of the conſpirators, but that the definitive ſentence of Condemnation muſt be pronounced againſt them, the aforeſaid <hi>Iohn Devoreux,</hi> Marſhall of the Court, and for that time the Kings Lieutenant, adjudged them this heavie doome; That the ſaid Archbiſhop of York, Duke of Ireland, Earle of Suffolke, <hi>Treſſilian,</hi> and <hi>Brambre,</hi> ſhould be drawne from the Tower to Tyborne, and there to bee hanged upon a Gibbet untill they were dead, and all their Lands and Goods to be confiſcated, that none of their poſterity might be by them any way enriched.</p>
            <p>On the 12. day of February, which was the firſt day of Shrovetide, <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Brambre</hi> appeared in Parliament; and being charged with the aforeſaid Articles of Treaſon, he craved favour to adviſe of Counſell learned, and ſome longer time for his more full anſwer to his accuſation: But the Judges char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to anſwer ſeverally to every point in the Articles contained: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <hi>Brambre</hi> anſwered, Whoſoever hath branded me with this ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous marke, with him I am ready to fight in the Liſts, to maintaine my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, whenſoever the King ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p>The Appellants hearing this couragious challenge, with reſolute counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance anſwered, That they would willingly accept of the Combat, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon flung downe their Gages before the King; and on a ſudden the whole company of Lords, Knights, Eſquires, and Commons, flung downe their Gages ſo thicke, that they ſeemed like Snow in a Winters day, crying out. We alſo will accept of the Combat, and will prove theſe Articles to be true to thy head, moſt damnable Traytor, and ſo they departed for that day.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:112175:7"/>
And although the Appellants were not idle in the night, yet on the next day, to aggravate their Appellation againſt the Conſpira ors, there came di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers companies of the City of London, complaining of the manifold inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they had ſuffered by <hi>Brambre,</hi> and other Extortions and Exactions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they had beene daily charged.</p>
            <p>But before they proceed with his tryall, they were ſtayed by moſt unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <hi>Treſſilian,</hi> who being got upon the top of an houſe adjoyning to the Palace, and had deſcended into a gutter onely to looke about him, hee was diſcovered by certaine of the Peeres, who preſently ſent ſome of the Guard to apprehend him, who entring into the houſe where hee was, and having ſpent long time in vaine in looking for him, at length one of the Guard ſtept to the Maſter of the houſe, and taking him by the ſhoulder, with his dagger drawne, thus ſaid, Shew us where thou haſt hid <hi>Treſſilian,</hi> or elſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve thy dayes are accompliſhed: the Maſter trembled, ready to yeeld up the ghoſt for fare, anſwered, Yonder is the place where he lyes, and ſhews him a round Table covered with branches of Bay, under which <hi>Treſſilian</hi> lay cloſe covered; when they had found him, they drew him out by the heeles, wondring to ſee him, as Vipers uſe, to weare his head and beard o're-grown, with old clowted ſhooes, and patched hoſe, more like a miſerable poore beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, then a Judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Treſſilian</hi> being come into the Hall, was asked what he could ſay for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, why judgement ſhould not paſſe upon him for his treaſon ſo often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, he became as one that had beene ſtrucke dumbe, and his heart was as it were hardned to the very laſt, and would not confeſſe himſelfe guilty of any thing: And for this cauſe the Parliament aroſe, deferring <hi>Brambres</hi> try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all till the next day. But <hi>Treſſilian</hi> was without delay led to the Tower, that he might ſuffer the execution of the ſentence paſſed againſt him.</p>
            <p>Immediately <hi>Treſſilian</hi> is upon a hurdle, and drawne thorow the ſtreets of the City, with a wonderfull concourſe of people following him, at every furlongs end he was ſuffered to ſtand ſtill to reſt himſelfe, and to ſee if hee would confeſſe and report himſelfe of any thing, but what hee ſaid to the Fryer his Confeſſor is not knowne, neither am I able to ſearch it out; when he came to the place of execution hee would not climbe the Ladder, untill ſuch time as being ſoundly beaten with bats and ſtaves, he was forced to goe up, and when he was up, he ſaid, ſo long as I doe weare any thing upon me I ſhall not dye, wherefore the Executioner ſtripped him, and found certaine Images painted like to the ſignes of Heaven, and the head of a Devill pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the names of many of the Devils wrote in parchment, the exorci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing toyes being taken away, and he was hanged up naked, and becauſe the ſpectators ſhould bee certainly aſſured that hee was dead, they cut his throat, and becauſe the night approached, they let him hang untill the next
<pb facs="tcp:112175:7"/>
morning, and then his wife having obtained a licence of the King, tooke downe his body and carried it to the Grey-Fryers, where it was buried. On the morow ſentence was likewiſe pronounced againſt <hi>Brambre,</hi> who being drawne upon a hurdle from the Tower to Tyborne thorow the City, ſhewed himſelfe very penitent, humbly craving mercy and forgiveneſſe at the hands of God and men, whom he had ſo grievouſly offended, and whom he had ſo injuriouſly wronged in time paſt, and did earneſtly deſire them all to pray for him; when the rope was about his necke ready to be turned off, a certaine young man, the ſonne of one <hi>Northampton,</hi> asked if he had done juſtice to his Father or not, for <hi>Northampton</hi> was ſometimes Maior of the City of <hi>London</hi> more wealthy and more ſubſtantiall then any elſe in the City, him did <hi>Brambre</hi> &amp; <hi>Treſilian</hi> accuſe of Treaſon and Conſpiracie againſt the State, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to die, being diſpoiled of his eſtate, he himſelf at length hardly eſcaped, to whom <hi>Brambre</hi> anſwered and confeſſed with bitter tears that what he did was moſt vile and wicked, and with an intent onely to murder and overthrow the ſaid <hi>Northampton,</hi> for which craving pardon of the young man being ſuddenly turned off, and the Executioner cutting his throat, he dyed.</p>
            <p>Theſe men being diſpatched, the Parliament diſcontinued their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt the reſt of the Conſpirators till a more convenient time, and tooke into their conſiderations other more weighty affaires of the weale publicke, they made the Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> Lord Admirall, giving him autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to reſiſt and to repulſe either by Sea or Land the enemies of the Crowne whereſoever he ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inde them.</p>
            <p>And it was further agreed on, that for the appeaſing of all private diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents (if any were) the King and the reſt of the Appellants with the reſt of the Commiſſioners ſhould dine together in the great Hall, which they did, and there was great joy at this reconciliation throw all the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>When theſe things were concluded, they then began this arraignment of the Traytors, whereupon <hi>John Blake</hi> and <hi>Thomas Vske</hi> were indicted on the fourth day of March, who although they were men of inferiout quality, yet were they found to be parties in the ſaid Treaſon; <hi>Vske</hi> was a Sergeant at Armes, and was indicted amongſt the Conſpirators, ſo that being late made Sheriffe of <hi>Middleſex</hi> he had indicted the five Appellants and the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners as Traytors, and <hi>Blake</hi> was an Intelligencer of <hi>Treſilians,</hi> one that uſed to goe and come between the Conſpirators, and relate the ſtate and ſucceſſe of the treaſon from one to another.</p>
            <p>And when they could ſay nothing to prove themſelves cleare, ſentence was pronounced upon them as their Maſters were before them, they were carried to the Tower, and from thence were dragged at the horſe tayle to Tyborne, and there hanged.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Vske</hi> obtained this favour, that his head was cut off after he was han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:112175:8"/>
and ſet aloft upon Newgate for Fowles of the aire to take repaſt.</p>
            <p>On the ſixth day of March there were called to anſwer, <hi>Robert Belknap, John Holt, Roger Falthorpe, William Burleigh, John Locton,</hi> and <hi>John Carey</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of the Exchequer for their conſpiracie againſt the Commiſſioners at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> but becauſe it is not needfull to rehearſe every part of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, they were all condemned like as the reſt.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Peeres were trying them, the Clergie were retired into the Kings Chambers, but when word was brought to them of the condemnation of the Judges, the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> the Chancellor, the Treaſurer, Lord Keeper of the Privie Seale aroſe haſtily and went into the Parliament Houſe, powring forth their complaints before the King and the Peeres humbly upon their knees, beſeeching them for the love of God, the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and of all the Saints, even as they hoped to have mercy at the day of Judgement, they ſhould ſhew favour, and not put to death the ſaid Judges then preſent, and bitterly bewayling their iniquities in whoſe hearts the very life, ſoule, and ſpirit of our Engliſh Lawes lived, flouriſhed and appeared, and there appeared great ſorrow both on the one part of the Complainants and alſo of the Defendants.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> likewiſe with the Earles of <hi>Arundel, Warwicke, Nottingham,</hi> and <hi>Derby,</hi> whoſe hearts began to be mollified, and joyned with them in their latnentable Petition.</p>
            <p>At length upon the interceſſion of the Clergie, the execution upon the perſons was ceaſed, and their lives were granted them, but were ſent to the Tower to be kept cloſe priſoners.</p>
            <p>On the twelfth of March, being Thurſday, it happened that the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Knights, <hi>Simon de Burleigh, John de Beauchamy, James Baroverſe,</hi> and <hi>John Saleſbury</hi> were brought into the Parliament Houſe where their accuſations was read, proved, they found guilty, and not any way able to cleare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>From this day almoſt till the Aſcenſion of our Lord, the Parliament Houſe was only taken up with the tryall of Sir <hi>Symon Burleygh,</hi> for three Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, <hi>viz.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> the Earles of <hi>Arundel</hi> and <hi>Warwick,</hi> with the whole Houſe of Commons, urged that execution might be performed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law: and on the other ſide, the King and Queen, the Earles of <hi>Darby</hi> and <hi>Nottingham,</hi> and the Prior of Saint <hi>John</hi> his Uncle, with the major part of the upper Houſe, did labour to have him ſaved.</p>
            <p>There was alſo ſome muttering amongſt the common people, and it was reported to the Parliament that the Commons did riſe in divers parts of the Realm, but eſpecially about <hi>Kent,</hi> in favour of the ſaid Sir <hi>Simon Burleigh,</hi> which when they heard thoſe that before ſpake and ſtood for him, now flew clean from him, and by joynt conſent on the fifth day of May, ſentence was
<pb facs="tcp:112175:8"/>
pronounced only againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>Simon,</hi> that he ſhould be drawne from the Tower to Tyborne, and then to be hanged till he were dead, and then to have his head ſtrooke from his body. But becauſe he was a Knight of the Gaiter, a gallant Courtier. powerfull, and once a Favourite of the Kings, and much reſpected of all the Court, the King of his ſpeciall Grace, was pleaſed to mittigate his doome, that he ſhould only be led to Tower-hill, and there be beheaded.</p>
            <p>On the twelfth of May, the Thurſday before Whitſontide, in like manner were condemned <hi>John Beuchamp</hi> Steward of the houſhold to the King, <hi>James Bereverous,</hi> and <hi>John Salsbury</hi> Knights, Gentlemen of the privie Chamber, whereof the two firſt, <hi>viz. John Beuchamp,</hi> and <hi>James Bereverous</hi> were behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on Tower-hill, but <hi>John Salsbury</hi> was drawne from Tower-hill to Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, and there was hanged.</p>
            <p>On the ſame day alſo, was condemned the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> the Kings Confeſſor, but becauſe of his great dignity, he was pardoned.</p>
            <p>And alſo concerning the tranſlation of ſome Biſhops, becauſe Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſixth, after it came to his ears, that the Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to avoid all hope of Irregularity, he created him Archbiſhop of S. <hi>Andrews</hi> in <hi>Scotland:</hi> which Archbiſhop was under the power of <hi>Scots,</hi> enemies to the Crown; and in the gift of the Arch-Pope: and becauſe the Pope did chalenge halfe the title of all <hi>England</hi> to maintaine his wars, but although he craved it, yet he was denied: therefore he dealt warily and craftily; hoping to make up his mouth by the tranſlation of Biſhops: the Biſhop of <hi>Fly</hi> then Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, was made Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi> ſucceeded in his place; the Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells</hi> in his place: the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> in his place, and the Lord <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Waltham</hi> Lord-keeper of the privie Seale in his place; and this by his tranſlation of Biſhops he gained himſelf much money, according to the laws of the Canon; and when this came to the ears of the Parliament, that ſuch a ſum of money ſhould be tranſported out of the Land, they ſtrove what they could to hinder it, but could not, becauſe the Clergie gave their conſent.</p>
            <p>On the laſt day of May, the King appointed both Houſes to meet at <hi>Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mington</hi> whereas they made a concluſion of all the trialls of the ſaid treaſon, granting licenſe to <hi>Thomas Trenet, William Ellingham,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Nagworth</hi> Knights, <hi>Richard Metford, Iohn Slake, Iohn Lincolne,</hi> Clerkes to put in bail pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they were ſufficient, and to go into a place of <hi>England</hi> where they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, without any let or hindrance of any of the Kings Officers. Moreover, the ſix Juſtices, with the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> who ſtood condemned with them, were ſent into <hi>Ireland,</hi> there to remain for a tearm of life, &amp; thus they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, <hi>viz. Rob. Belknap</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn Holr</hi> in the Village of <hi>Dromore</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> not to remain as Juſtices or any officers, but live as baniſhed offenders, not to
<pb facs="tcp:112175:9"/>
be out of Towne above the ſpace of two miles upon paine of death? but the King out of his gracious bounty was pleaſed to give a yearly annuity of 40. pound to <hi>Robert Belknap,</hi> of twenty markes to <hi>Iohn Holt,</hi> during their lives; and to <hi>Roger Fulthrope</hi> the King allowed forty pound, and to <hi>William Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi> forty pound during life, confining them to the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> granting <hi>Burleigh</hi> the liberty of two miles, and to <hi>Fulthrope</hi> three miles for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, <hi>John Carey</hi> and <hi>John Locton</hi> with the yearly allowance of twenty pound during life, are confined to the Towne of <hi>Waterford</hi> with the like li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and the like penalty; And the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> is likewiſe ſent to <hi>Corke,</hi> there to remaine with ſome allowance, and the like penalty.</p>
            <p>On the third day of June, which was the laſt day of the Parliament, the King, the Queen, the Peeres of both Eſtates with the Commons, came to the Abbey at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> whereas the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> becauſe it was his Dioceſſe ſung Maſſe, and the Maſſe being ended, the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> made an Oration concerning the forme and danger of the Oath, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, although the Peers and Commons had taken the Oath of Allegiance, and homage to the King, yet becauſe the King was young when they tooke Oath anew (as at the firſt) at his Coronation.</p>
            <p>Theſe Ceremonies being performed, the Metropolitan of <hi>England</hi> with all his Suffragans there preſent, having lighted a Candle, and putting it under a ſtoole, put it out, thereby excommunicating all ſuch as ſhould ſeeme to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſte, diſlike or contradict any of the fore paſſed Acts in the laſt Parliament; And the Lord Chancellor by the Kings appointment, cauſed all that were preſent to ſweare to keep the ſaid Statutes inviolably whole, and undiſſolved, as good and faithfull Liege-people of the Kings, and the forme of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was obſerved throughout all the Realme.</p>
            <p>On the morrow, which was the fourth day of June, many courteous falu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and congratulations having paſſed betweene the King, the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Communalty, the Parliament was diſſolved, and every man returned home.</p>
            <p>And now let <hi>England</hi> rejoyce in Chriſt, for the net which was laid ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly for our deſtruction, is broken aſunder, and we are delivered. To God be the praiſe for all.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>This Parliament begunne at Weſtminſter <date>1386. in the tenth yeare of the reigne of King <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
